Finding Aid for the Bob Balser Papers LSC.2173
UCLA Library Special Collections
Bob Balser papers
1955-circa 2000s
1970-2000
UCLA Library Special Collections
Balser, Bob
LSC.2173
13 linear feet (15 boxes, 12 flat boxes, 2 shoe boxes, and 1 carton)
Bob Balser has been involved in animation production and direction since the 1950s. The collection consists of production-related material for animated projects produced by Bob Balser and his animation studio Pegbar, a small amount of material documenting Balser's involvement with the European Animation Circle, and small number of animation-related publications.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed audiovisual materials. For information about the access status of the material that you are looking for, refer to the Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the file levels. All requests to access processed audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Bob and Cima Balser, 2013.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9971992493606533
Biography
Robert (Bob) Balser was born March 25, 1927 in Rochester, New York. Received a B.A in Advertising Arts from the University of California, Los Angeles (1959). Balser started his animation career in 1955 working for Norman Wright Productions doing animation-lay-out. He moved abroad in the early 1960s where he settled in Barcelona, Spain. During the late-1960s to early 1970s he co-directed the feature animated film, Yellow Submarine (1968) and was supervision director for the television animation program The Jackson 5. In 1972 he formed the company PEGBAR Productions and continued to turn out a number of animated feature films and television programs such as the Emmy award winning The Lion, The Witch and The Wardrobe and Fangface. He is an active member of the International Association of animated Film (A.S.I.F.A) and A.S.I.F.A-Spain and in leadership capacity in both. He is also active in the European Association of Animated Film and has been a member of International Film Festival Juries.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of material related to the career of animation director Bob Balser and his animation studio Pegbar. Productions represented include Barney, Baydogs, Fangface, The Fantastic World of Minus, Professor Van Dussen's Mysterious Cases, and Off to the New World, among others. Types of material vary for each project and may include: proposals, scripts, and photocopies and occasional original artwork such as animation stock scenes, storyboards, layouts, and model sheets. Also included is a small amount of material documenting Balser's involvement with the European Animation Circle and small number of animation-related publications including children's books, magazines, and catalogs. Some materials in the collection are in Spanish.
Animators -- Archives.; Balser, Bob--Archives
- A gua que bebemos publication, 1982 (Box 3)
- Academy Awards invitations and ephemera for the 72nd and 74th Annual awards, 2000, 2004 (Box 14)
- Academy Awards reminder lists, rules, and schedules (9 items), 1997-2001 (Box 14)
- AFI Report: Animation, 1974 (Box 3)
- Alexandrow Glauert Film and AV Produktion GMBH company, undated (Box 13)
- Alexandrow Glauert Film and AV Produktion GMBH, Tope Film, and European Animation Circle - contracts and legal documents, 1989-1992 (Box 7)
- Alexandrow Glauert Film and AV Produktion GMBH, Tope Film, and European Animation Circle - contracts and legal documents, 1990-1992 (Box 6)
- Alf Laila Wa-Laila (A Thousand and One Nights) - project portfolio, 1992 (Box 9)
- Alfred in Wonderland - presentation (2 items), undated (Box 5)
  General note
  With Oscar, Secret Agent plot summary.
- American Cinematographer magazine, 1982 (Box 28)
- Animation catalogue Europe, 1993 (Box 24)
- Animation Magazine (19 items), 1997-2012 (Box 26)
- Animation Magazine (7 items), 1987-1989 (Box 28)
- Animatographe magazine, 1987 (Box 30)
- Anna Miquel catalog (2 items), undated, 1991 (Box 3)
- Articles about animation written in Spanish, undated, 1992 (Box 14)
- Artype tenth anniversary catalog, 1955 (Box 3)
- ASIFA 30th Anniversary catalog, 1990 (Box 25)
- ASIFA Annie Awards programs (3 items), 2007-2009 (Box 26)
- ASIFA Italy animation studio directory, 1991-1992 (Box 25)
- ASIFA List of Animation Schools (2 items), undated (Box 25)
- ASIFA Magazine (8 items), 2003-2004, 2008-2010 (Box 26)
- ASIFA Magazine Canada, 1998 (Box 26)
- Association Internationale du Film d'Animation (ASIFA) material, undated (Box 25)
- Assorted documents, magazines, and correspondence, undated (Box 30)
- Atelier Animation Annecy 20th Anniversary, undated (Box 30)
- Audiocassette tapes (20 items), undated (Box 2)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Auidovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted below. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
  - Fang Face, 1979 May 11; yrlsc_2173_002_001; Balser, Bob; 1 sound recordings (1 audiocassette; Duration: 00:11:08) (Box 2, Case 1)
    CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials are available for access. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - The Story of Color, undated; yrlsc_2173_002_002; 1 sound recordings (1 audiocassette; Duration: 00:23:25) (Box 2, Case 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Transcribed from container: "The Story of Color" Border and Company Fostertown Rd. Medford, New Jersey USA 609-235-8222
  - Highlights of Score "Story of Color", undated; yrlsc_2173_002_003a; 1 sound recordings (1 audiocassette; Duration: 00:09:39) (Box 2, Case 3)
  - Complete Selections of Score "Story of Color", undated; yrlsc_2173_002_003b; 1 sound recordings (1 audiocassette; Duration: 00:14:08) (Box 2, Case 3)
- Audiocassette tapes (30 items), undated (Box 1)
  CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Auidovisual materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
- Aviones, 1971 (Box 3)
- Barnaby y los fantasmas, 1988 (Box 3)
- Barney - books, 1988 (Box 7)
- Barney - correspondence, production contract, proposal, and budget information, 1987-1989 (Box 7)
- Barney - illustrations, undated (Box 16)
- Barney - model sheet photocopies, ca. 1988 (Box 15)
- Barney - model sheet photocopies, undated (Box 15)
- Barney - model sheets photocopies, undated (Box 16)
- Barney - presentation, undated (Box 7)
- Barney - storyboard photocopies, undated (Box 7)
- Barney Gets Ready for Christmas - outline, undated (Box 7)
- Barrabs and La Codorniz - magazines, 1975 (Box 16)
- Baydog - audiocasette tapes (5 items), undated (Box 1)
- Baydog - layouts (7 folders), undated (Box 11)
- Baydog - model sheet photocopies, undated (Box 7)
- Baydog - model sheet photocopies, undated (Box 7)
- Baydog - presentation, undated (Box 9)
- Baydog - script and correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 9)
- Baydog - scripts (4 items), undated (Box 9)
- Baydog - storyboard photocopies (9 items), ca. 1998 (Box 8)
- Biennale d'illustration (La), 1985 (Box 3)
- Blanket (The) by Quinn Donoghue - short story, 1993 (Box 5)
- Broadcast Systems Engineering tearouts assorted tutorial on television production techniques, 1985 (Box 29)
- Brunhilda - model sheet photocopies, undated (Box 15)
- Campana catalogs (5 items), 1978, 1986-1989 (Box 10)
- Cartoon Forum board minutes (20 items), ca. late 1980s - early 2000s (Box 25)
- Cartoon Forum catalogs (5 items), 1990-1991, 1993 (Box 30)
- Cartoon studio groupings, no date, 1989-1990 (Box 25)
- Cartoons: The International Journal of Animation (5 items), 2005-2007 (Box 28)
- Cineinforme - magazines (4 items), 1990-1991 (Box 28)
- Cinematografo, 1988 (Box 3)
- Cinevideo magazines (2 items), 1990, 1993 (Box 28)
- Company portfolio, undated (Box 13)
- Correspondence between Bob Balser and Quinn Donoghue regarding various projects, 1989-1992 (Box 5)
- Crespo La Espanola Olive advertisement - correspondence, character sketches, and storyboard, 1993 (Box 5)
- Cuts - magazine, 1993 (Box 3)
- Daring Dozen (The) - synopses, proposal, and sample episode, 1992 (Box 5)
  With holographic notes regarding Minus.
- Der Zauberwald - storyboard and scene analysis, undated (Box 9)
- Doglantis - model sheet photocopies, script pages, and treatment, ca. 1998 (Box 9)
- Doncella Guerrera (La) - registration papers and scene outlines, 1983, 1974 (Box 5)
- El libroWalt Disney de las palabras (2 items), 1972 (Box 3)
- El mundo de la aviacion, 1970 (Box 3)
- El tebeo del sal - magazine, 1988 (Box 3)
- Estudios Moros - model sheet photocopies, undated (Box 15)
- European Animation Circle - flyers, undated (Box 13)
- Fangface - stock scenes (10 folders), undated (Box 19)
- Fangface - stock scenes (12 folders), undated (Box 22)
- Fangface - stock scenes (12 folders), undated (Box 21)
- Fangface - stock scenes (12 folders), undated (Box 18)
- Fangface - stock scenes (19 folders), undated (Box 20)
- Fangface - stock scenes (4 folders), undated (Box 16)
- Fangface - stock scenes (6 folders), undated (Box 23)
- Fangface - stock scenes (8 folders), undated (Box 17)
- Fantastic Mon d'en Minus - project portfolio Catalan master copy, undated (Box 12)
- Fantastic Mon d'en Minus - project portfolio, undated (Box 14)
- Fantastic Mon d'en Minus - scripts, episode synopses, and production charts, undated (Box 12)
- Fantastic Mon d'en Minus - treatment and character model sheet photocopies`, undated (Box 12)
- Fantastic World of Minus (The) - artwork photocopies, undated (Box 15)
- Fantastic World of Minus (The) - artwork photocopies and storyboard photocopies, undated (Box 15)
- Fantastic World of Minus (The) - Cartoon Forum project portfolio master copy, undated (Box 12)
- Fantastic World of Minus (The) - contract and letters, 1990-1991 (Box 6)
- Fantastic World of Minus (The) - contract with synopsis and storyboard photocopies, 1990 (Box 12)
- Fantastic World of Minus (The) - flyer mock-up and copies, undated (Box 12)
- Fantastic World of Minus (The) - production charts, undated (Box 23)
- Fantastic World of Minus (The) - project portfolio master copy, undated (Box 12)
- Fantastic World of Minus (The) - sales history, 1990-1993 (Box 12)
  jg check: is it really?
- Fantastic World of Minus (The) - script pages and storyboard photocopies (9 items), undated (Box 14)
- Fantastic World of Minus (The) - storyboard photocopies (18 items), undated (Box 14)
- Fantastic World of Minus (The)/Le fantastique monde du Minus - project portfolio, undated (Box 14)
- Fantastic World of Minus (The)/Le fantastique monde du Minus - project portfolio, undated (Box 14)
- Fantastic World of Minus (The)/Le fantastique monde du Minus - project portfolio (2 items), undated (Box 14)
- Fernando Krahn drawings, no date, 1984 (Box 25)
- Film in Review - mailer, 1988 (Box 29)
- Flax - catalog, 1971 (Box 3)
- Forest of Magic (The) - script, 1985 (Box 9)
- French production directory, 1991 (Box 29)
- Here We Are - published script photocopies, undated (Box 7)
- Hermano Lobo, 1975 (Box 23)
- Horse cycle - model sheet photocopies, undated (Box 15)
- II Mostra Cinema Animaci programs and postcards (7 items), 1987 (Box 29)
- III Mostra Cinema Animaci programs (3 items), undated (Box 29)
- Immagine per immagine, 1989 (Box 3)
- IV Mostra Cinema Animaci programs (3 items), 1989 (Box 29)
- Josette Janssens Graphica, 1986 (Box 3)
- Latest Rage (The) - project portfolio, 1991 (Box 9)
- LAUS ADGFAD, undated (Box 3)
- L'echo des Savanes - magazine, 1987 (Box 9)
- Limpioncete - character model sheet photocopies, undated (Box 5)
- Little Grey Rabbit's Birthday - script, undated (Box 5)
- Magic Forest (The) - project portfolio (2 items), 1990 (Box 9)
- Magic Forest/Bosque Magico - model sheet photocopies, undated, 1992 (Box 16)
- Marsh Brother (The)/Tmpel and Co. - project portfolio, undated (Box 13)
- Marsh Brother (The)/Tmpel and Co. - project portfolio, undated (Box 13)
- Marsh Brother (The)/Tmpel and Co. - project portfolio (3 items), undated (Box 13)
- Marsh Brothers (The) - episode summaries and storyboard, undated (Box 14)
- Mayflower Mascots (The) - project portfolio, 1992 (Box 9)
- Mayflower Mascots (The) - project portfolio mock-up, 1992 (Box 5)
- Mayflower Mascots (The) - project portfolio with character model sheet photocopies, 1992 (Box 5)
- Mayflower Mascots (The) - project portfolio with Five-Minute Mysteries photocopies, 1992 (Box 5)
- Media newsletters (15 items), 1988, 1990-1993, 1996 (Box 29)
- Media: Progress Report of the Pilot Projects, 1990 (Box 24)
- Mi primer gran libro del aire, 1975 (Box 3)
- Mi primer gran libro para reir, 1974 (Box 3)
- Minus - bills, 1992-1993 (Box 6)
- Minus - contracts, 1992-1993 (Box 6)
- Minus - correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
- Minus - storyboard and script pages, undated (Box 6)
- Mssan, 1981 (Box 3)
- Muzei Mimara catalog, undated (Box 30)
- Never Ending Story - correspondence, character model sheet photocopies, project portfolio, and budget information, 1992-1993 (Box 5)
- Nim-Pops - storyboards, undated (Box 15)
- Off to the New World - business letters and proposal material, 1990 (Box 5)
- Off to the New World - Cartoon Forum project portfolio mock-up, undated (Box 5)
- Off to the New World - character model sheet photocopies, 1990 (Box 5)
- Off to the New World - episode one script, 1990 (Box 13)
- Off to the New World - episode one script (3 items), 1990 (Box 5)
- Off to the New World - flyers, undated (Box 5)
- Off to the New World - project portfolio Spanish master copy, undated (Box 13)
- Off to the New World - project portfolios and character model sheet photocopies, undated (Box 12)
- Off to the New World - proposal, 1990 (Box 5)
- Off to the New World - proposal, 1990 (Box 5)
- Off to the New World - Spanish project portfolio, undated (Box 5)
- Off to the New World/Hacia el nuevo mundo - project portfolio (3 items), undated (Box 9)
- Off to the New World/Vers le nouveau monde - flyers, undated (Box 13)
- Off to the New World/Vers le nouveau monde - project portfolio, undated (Box 9)
- Off to the New World/Vers le nouveau monde - project portfolio (3 items), undated (Box 13)
- Pegbar advertisement, undated, 1976-1977 (Box 6)
- Pegbar bills, 1984-1985 (Box 7)
- Pegbar blank storyboard forms, undated (Box 7)
- Pegbar business records, 1981-1983, 1985 (Box 6)
- Pegbar dossier flyers, undated (Box 13)
- Pegbar fiscal papers, 1991, 1993 (Box 6)
- Pegbar production records, ca. 1970s-1990s (Box 6)
- Pegbar registration, 1991, 1993 (Box 6)
- Popeye - sketches, illustration photocopies, and comic, undated, 1970 (Box 15)
- Popeye comic in Japanese, 1977 (Box 3)
- Pop'set - catalog, 1992 (Box 3)
- Professor van Dusen's Criminal Adventures/Les aventures policieres de Prof. van Dusen - project portfolio, undated (Box 13)
- Professor van Dusen's Mysterious Cases - project portfolio, undated (Box 13)
- Professor van Dusen's Mysterious Cases - project portfolio (2 items), undated (Box 13)
- Professor van Dusen's Mysterious Cases - project portfolio (3 items), undated (Box 13)
- Professor van Dusen's Mysterious Cases - project portfolio, character model sheet photocopies, and calculations for one sequence, ca. 1990 (Box 12)
- Project portfolio master copies, undated (Box 12)
- Raimon Sunyer - catalog, undated (Box 3)
- Santa and the Tooth Fairies - project portfolio, undated (Box 13)
- Sequences TV-Video, undated (Box 28)
- Sequences: revue de cinema, 1984 (Box 28)
- Silabario Disney, 1971 (Box 3)
- Sleeping Beauty - model sheet photocopies, undated (Box 15)
- Spanish language comic books and comic book pages (11 items), undated (Box 9)
- Stiges Festival, 1993 (Box 6)
- The Whole Toon Catalog, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
- Topolino e poi, 1978 (Box 3)
- Totem - magazine, undated (Box 28)
- Tres Bessones (Los) - storyboard pages, undated (Box 6)
- Triplets (The) - flyers, undated (Box 13)
- Triplets (The) - project portfolio, undated (Box 13)
- Un viaje en tren, 1972 (Box 3)
- Upper and Lower Case, The International Journal of Typographics (21 items), 1983-1988, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
- Variety, 1991 (Box 16)
- Variety 68th Anniversary Edition, 1974 (Box 16)
- Variety Europe Focus On: Animation (2 items), 1992 (Box 16)
- Various brochures from festival presentations (1/3 record storage carton), no date, ca. 1970s-1990s (Box 24)
- Various model sheets, undated (Box 15)
- Various model sheets, undated (Box 15)
- Various project porfolios not related to European Animation Circle (21 items), no date, ca. 1980s-1990s (Box 27)
- Viva el algodn!, 1972 (Box 3)
- Winsor-Newton catalog, undated (Box 30)
- Work permits, etc., ca. 1970s-1990s (Box 7)
- Zoom - magazine, 1976 (Box 3)